<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Stalking the Programing World - Jenkins</title><link href="http://www.progmad.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.progmad.com/feeds/jenkins.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.progmad.com/</id><updated>2017-09-06T11:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>JenkinsWorld 2017, How to use Jenkins less and be more productive as a team.</title><link href="http://www.progmad.com/2017/09/jenkinsworld2017-summary/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-09-06T11:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-06T11:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Philip Marc Schwartz</name></author><id>tag:www.progmad.com,2017-09-06:/2017/09/jenkinsworld2017-summary/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Review of JenkinsWorld 2017 with key takeaways.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2 id="jenkins-certified-engineer-training"&gt;Jenkins Certified Engineer Training&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The training given by opensourcearchitect was very straight forward. It covered all of the topics 
expected along with a jaunt into CloudBees specific features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best note of this was the introduction to CloudBees Jenkins Operations Center (CJOC). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This provides wonderful management and automated features around:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Authentication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Authorization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Elastic Master Management&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plugin Management&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automated Job Spreading using Jenkins Job DSL&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are all things that were very painful with OSS Jenkins and it will be fun to see them 
come together on an enterprise level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And as a final note from the 2 day training, I am now a Certified Jenkins Engineer. This allows
for just another certification to my name and expertise to help other on my team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="jenkinsworld"&gt;JenkinsWorld&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was my first time attending JenkinsWorld, but not my first technical conference. The atmosphere
was much of the same, and many sessions tended towards the marketing and work of teams. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This made choosing which sessions to attend and which not very difficult, but with some effort,
I feel that I gained a new understanding for Jenkins and the Pipeline workflow. But most importantly,
I learned that I have been looking at it the wrong way for many years. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets dig deeper into this!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="pipeline-unit-testing"&gt;Pipeline Unit Testing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thursday morning, I had a very good conversation with Ozan Gunalp and Emmanuel Quincerot. Both are software
engineers from LesFurets.com. But in the Jenkins world, they are known for their work on the
JenkinsPipelineUnit project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project presents a series of entrypoints and mocking features around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using this library is as easy as the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;com.lesfurets.jenkins.unit.BasePipelineTest&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="kd"&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;TestExample&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kd"&gt;extends&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;BasePipelineTest&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="nd"&gt;@Test&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="kt"&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;baserun_without_errors&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kd"&gt;throws&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Exception&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="kt"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;jenkinsfile&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;loadScript&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;./jenkinsfile&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;jenkinsfile&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;execute&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;printCallStack&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="o"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This provides a very nice comparable output, along with a junit test return for good display in Jenkins&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;jenkinsfile.run()
jenkinsfile.edpGlobal.runEdpProcess()
    ... Call stack based on full run
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is one downfall of using this library and that is its requirement on deep groovy reflection. This 
limits its use in deeply inherited and factory generated code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With future refactorization of code, I hope to work toward fully implemented test cases for the full
T-Mobile EDP Pipeline based on this library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="using-jenkins-less"&gt;Using Jenkins Less&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesse Glick gave a very good talk on how to "Use Jenkins Less". This was focused on the ideas of moving from
traditional jenkins freestyle jobs to Jenkins Pipeline jobs and what was needed to obtain this on a long term
usable model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesse had a very good example of a code linting tool for Java that many projects have been using and are now
in trouble due to the plugin being deprecated by the company owning the plugin and with a statement of not
opensourcing the plugin to allow another developer to maintain it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This lead to the thought that the usage of Jenkins plugins should be limited as much as possible to prevent
any chance of your pipeline being unable to work post an update or between Jenkins masters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flow of this talk lead to the idea that freestyle jobs are best for maintainability because you can 
do everything via shell scripting. But with freestyle jobs not being ideal for usage in complex projects and
not having a valid display in Blue Ocean, that pipeline jobs are the next best thing and considered only
slightly more complex. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This provided a few strong points that all users should attempt to follow:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep the pipeline simple, it is built to be an orchestration layer not a build or automation script.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put build logic in external scripts if possible, to avoid things like @NonCPS and method whitelisting problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use shell steps over all else.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first of these points is very easy to follow. A pipeline should be a high level orchestration and nothing
more. When you get to forcing build customization and automation into your pipeline scripts, you have stepped
beyond what a pipeline script should do. As part of this, all imported code should be concise and contained 
in a single standard groovy file that is importable with the pipeline LibraryStep.LoadedClasses object.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This ties into how the JenkinsPipelineUnit library works and how its reflection does not dig into deep
inheritance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second point shows the idea of using many external scripts that are perferably stored in an SCM and 
loaded with the Jenkins "load" step. This allows you to load a single script and access it directly via
a variable in a pipeline script.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third point is the biggest of the suggestions to follow. Most people attempt to use as many Jenkins
plugins as you can. This leads to many points that are not easy to debug inside of a pipeline. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example you can look at the Maven plugin and the pipeline withMaven wrapper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The maven plugin loads multiple jars that make up the maven entrypoint and then pass parameters to it. There
is no call to the mvn binary and debugging start up problems are very very hard. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When looking at the withMaven wrapper, you are able to see that unlike the maven plugin, the mvn binary
is called, but the call is wrapped in multiple property and parameter setters that alter its base
functionaility. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of a users lack of control over how these things work, the usage of them should be very 
sparing in order to maximize the reusability and stability of your pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a very long time, I worked to use as many jenkins plugins as possible as well as working to create
plugins to help with my workflow. Jesse's talk really opened my eyes to the right way to build a Jenkins
pipeline and how to keep it usable for a forseable future. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the talk on JenkinsPipelineUnit showed me that as I work to define clean pipelines, there is a 
way to provide strong unit testing as well as strong integration testing to make sure my pipelines
will always work. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am looking forward to working with my team to implement these ideas as well as making our pipelines
first rate pieces of software that are easily usable by all developers inside of T-Mobile&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="jenkins"></category><category term="automation"></category><category term="ci"></category><category term="cd"></category><category term="groovy"></category></entry></feed>